<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Economics on Dyrehaugen</title>
    <link>http://localhost/pde/categories/economics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Economics on Dyrehaugen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost/pde/categories/economics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Farewell Globalization</title>
      <link>http://localhost/pde/posts/2021-05-30-farewell-globalization/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost/pde/posts/2021-05-30-farewell-globalization/</guid>
      <description>To solve the Climate Crisis increasing economic productivity and energy efficiency is not sufficient. Absolute decoupling of economic growth and environmental degradition, including global warming is not feasible (Hickel and Kallis (2019) Is Green Growth Possible?). We will have to stop economic growth itself or even degrow on a global scale.
Growth economists have always had models that in the long run end in a steady state. That&amp;rsquo;s just mathematics. Many economists have been thinking about &amp;lsquo;steady state economics&amp;rsquo; for a long time.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>To solve the <em>Climate Crisis</em> increasing economic productivity and energy efficiency
is not sufficient.
Absolute <em>decoupling</em> of economic growth and environmental degradition, including
global warming is not feasible (Hickel and Kallis (2019) Is Green Growth Possible?).
We will have to <strong>stop economic growth itself</strong> or even <strong>degrow</strong>  on a global scale.</p>
<p>Growth economists have always had models that in the long run end in a <em>steady state</em>.
That&rsquo;s just mathematics.
Many economists have been thinking about &lsquo;steady state economics&rsquo; for a long time.
Wikipedia has an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steady-state_economy">overview</a>.</p>
<p>Most recent a new label has been introduced: <a href="https://doughnuteconomics.org/about-doughnut-economics">&lsquo;Doughnut Economy&rsquo;</a>.
The focus is on defining the <em>limits</em> within which the economy can operate without harming
the environment on the one side and providing for a good life for everybody on the other side.
Also focused is the new <em>practises</em> people and businesses can apply in developing
sustainablity principles - moving from &lsquo;exstractive&rsquo; to &lsquo;generative&rsquo; enterprises.</p>
<p>This is the optimistic bottom-up movement of buidling new practises - and is certainly important.</p>
<p>The other side of the coin is more pessimistic:</p>
<p>The world today consists also of the dark side: environmentally
harmfull &lsquo;practises&rsquo; on a large scale that have to be removed, and removed quickly.
These harmful practises contain the &lsquo;normal&rsquo;, &lsquo;business as usual&rsquo; ways of operating
for businesses and working people all over the world.
The really hard task ahead is to knock down these practises.</p>
<p>So, implementing a steady state (or degrowth) economy <strong>now</strong> - due to the
climate urgency ' is quite another issue than small-scale development of &lsquo;doughnut economics&rsquo;.</p>
<p>Herman Daly&rsquo;s famous book “A Steady-State Economy,” includes a 10-point
<em>Transition to a Steady State Economy (SSE)</em>-program.</p>
<p>Point 5 on the list is:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Re-regulate international commerce—move away from free trade, free capital mobility and globalization, adopt compensating tariffs to protect efficient national policies of cost internalization from standards-lowering competition from other countries.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Just this one point is a very tall order.
Actually, the task ahead is to <strong>undo all achievements of the liberal economic order that
has steered the world in recent decades</strong></p>
<p>How can it be done?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Case of Norway</title>
      <link>http://localhost/pde/posts/2021-02-26-the-case-of-norway/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost/pde/posts/2021-02-26-the-case-of-norway/</guid>
      <description>Nordic differences My Swedish friend Torbjörn just sent me a paper clip containing a notice of a Swedish economics professor commenting on the economic situation in Norway. Lars Calmfors in DN 22 feb 2021. The notice is triggered by his involvement in a Norwegian Green Paper Commision on Labour and Income Policy. NOU 2019:7. The Commision shouldpropose new measures to increase labour participation in Norway.
Internationally the Nordic (sometimes only Scandinavian) countries are mostly treated as fairly much of the same under the heading of &amp;lsquo;The Nordic Model&amp;rsquo;.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="nordic-differences">Nordic differences</h2>
<p>My Swedish friend Torbjörn just sent me a paper clip containing a notice of
a Swedish economics professor commenting on the economic situation in Norway.
<a href="https://www.dn.se/ledare/norsk-ekonomi-klarar-inte-bade-minskande-oljeintakter-och-hoga-ohalsotal/">Lars Calmfors in DN  22 feb 2021</a>. The notice is triggered by his involvement in a Norwegian
Green Paper Commision on Labour and Income Policy. <a href="https://www.regjeringen.no/no/dokumenter/nou-2019-7/id2637967/">NOU 2019:7</a>. The Commision shouldpropose new measures to increase labour participation in Norway.</p>
<p>Internationally the Nordic (sometimes only Scandinavian) countries are
mostly treated as fairly much of the same under the heading of &lsquo;The Nordic Model&rsquo;.
This article however points to the particularities of Norway compared to Sweden.</p>
<p>Calmfors&rsquo;s main point is that Norway will not be able to tackle both decreasing oil returns
and high levels of health-related labour market absense when at the same time the population
is quickly aging.</p>
<p>As expected the economists look to &lsquo;increased labour market participation&rsquo; as the
&lsquo;key factor&rsquo; to tackle the problems Norway is now fronting.
(This was in their mandate).</p>
<p>Compared to Sweden the percentage of people living on health-related social contributions are
much higher in Norway (17 pct around the double of Sweden).
Calmfors interprets this figure av &lsquo;medicalization of labour market problems&rsquo; -
which might for sure be true.</p>
<p>When discussing what to do about this situation the differences to Sweden come to the surface.
The Nowegian way is quite more corporativistic than what could happen in Sweden.
After receiving expert proposals from the economists the Commision is enlarged with
participants from Employers and Labour Unions plus from Government.
Together they are charged with finding (for all) acceptable ways forwards.</p>
<p>This way of working together (3-party co-operation) to me lies at the heart of the &lsquo;Nordic Model&rsquo;,
so I am a bit surprised by learning from Calmfors that this is not the way it works in Sweden?
May be the &lsquo;Norwegian Model&rsquo; is not the same as the &lsquo;Nordic Model&rsquo; after all?
Calmfors&rsquo;s conclusion is that this cooperative mode paired with strong egalitarian drives
will create great obstacles for getting more people involved on the labour market.</p>
<p>May be he is right in this. But to me it sounds like an argument to skip the core of
the &lsquo;Norwegian Model&rsquo; - for something more neo-liberalistic?
That would be out of date. The Reagan-Thatcher era is long gone - if not yet
among mainstream economists.</p>
<p>However, to my mind Norway faces problems at the end of the oil age that calls for
looking much more broadly into the strategy of economic transition for the coming decades.
Strikingly the issue of greening the economy is out of focus for this commision.
But let me first take a look at the workings of the &lsquo;Norwegian Model&rsquo; - which has been
in operation from the mid 1930s up till now - and may be longer?</p>
<h2 id="the-norwegian-way">The Norwegian Way</h2>
<p>An interesting analysis of the &lsquo;Scandinavian Model&rsquo; is found in
<a href="https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=&amp;cad=rja&amp;uact=8&amp;ved=2ahUKEwiIiJOpyIXvAhXQMMAKHW3WDi8QFjAAegQIAxAD&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Flanekenworthy.files.wordpress.com%2F2018%2F01%2Freading-barthetal2014.pdf&amp;usg=AOvVaw0zxuWR3J6zGPD5AMEgo2H6">Barth 2014 (pdf)</a></p>
<p>The conclusion of this work is as follows (my emphasis):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Why has the Scandinavian model worked so well? And, why have its
institutions and policies survived, in spite of changing economic and
political circumstances? Our answer to both questions is that there is a
<strong>strong complementarity between the Scandinavian non-market institutions
and capitalist dynamics</strong>.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Our paper emphasizes the political–economic equilibrium between
three sets of mechanisms. Encompassing organizations in the labor
market follow a policy of wage coordination and wage compression,
with a strong preference for full employment in central bargaining
and microeconomic efficiency in local bargaining. Wage compression
leads to a <strong>higher pace of creative destruction</strong> and further wage compression
with an increasing average wage. More wage equality and higher
average wages fuel the political support for welfare spending. There
might even be a feedback from public welfare policies to productivity
rise and further wage compression. This complementarity explains
why the same outcomes—efficiency and a high level of equality—could
not have been achieved by redistribution through the political system
alone.
This political-economic equilibrium path has benefitted from consistent
policies that have supplemented market forces. Active labor market
programs and moderations on employment protection have been important
policies to facilitate structural change and reallocation of labor
without excessive wage differentials.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A similar concern for consistency is evident from the extensive use of
‘work-fare’ policies, which are used in Denmark, Norway and Sweden to
ensure that work pays in the presence of generous welfare benefits.
High employment reduces the cost of a generous benefit system and increases the tax base.
Active job search or qualification efforts are for example required in order to obtain unemployment benefits.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In sum, the complementarity between the non-market institutions
and capitalist investments help explain why the main institutions and
policies have survived over 80 years. The gains are spread widely across
groups. There are many winners and few losers. Both low paid groups
and employers are clear winners as <strong>wage compression and rising profits
are two sides of the same coin</strong>. High skilled workers are potential losers.
But also high skilled workers may gain from wage moderation, as the
average productivity goes up.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The stability of the Scandinavian model can in part be explained by
the good performance, and the good performance must have been
helped by the stability of the model. The key is that both depend on
the egalitarian aspects of the Scandinavian model that share the gains
of good performance on almost all groups. Since the interactions be-
tween wage coordination, investments, and welfare spending all
strengthen the egalitarian aspects of the model, it would not be possible
to achieve the same egalitarian results by redistribution through the
welfare state only.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So - the &lsquo;Nordic / Scandinavian / Norwegian Model&rsquo; turns out to be just
a smart way to let capitalism evolve.
And it has worked well - on that premise - so far.</p>
<p>The model&rsquo;s &lsquo;golden age&rsquo; was before 1980.
But the neoliberal era - from 1980 onwards has created some dilemmas-
which might be read in the constant decline of the labour parties in
all the Nordic countries during the last couple of decades.</p>
<p>The alliance between Labour and Capital was based on mutual benefits:
Labour Organizations accepted wage restraints as long as capitalist
continued investing in project that created increade number of jobs.
However in the 1980&rsquo;s this closed loop was broken be globalization.
Capitalist&rsquo;s started putting the money into China and other developing
countries instead of investing at home.
Labour is no longer on the winning side of the play.
The gains are no longer as widely spread across groups.
As in other countries there is a rising precariate.</p>
<p>This has been most visible in the other Nordic countries - for Norway
the oil money came in between as a saving angel - allowing for
such &lsquo;economic diseases&rsquo; as 17% health-related social contributions to
people not participating in the labour market.
Thus, the coming end of the oil era put Norway up for greater challenges
than the other Nordic countries, as Calmfors rightly explained.</p>
<p>To green the economy while at the same time get out of &lsquo;oil addiction&rsquo;
is really a double challenge.</p>
<p>To find the way forwards one will need a lot more than main-stream
econmic thinking a la Calmfors.</p>
<p>A starting point could be an &lsquo;evolutionary economics&rsquo; approach.
Interesting extension in the understanding of how the &lsquo;Norwegian Model&rsquo; works
come from <a href="https://evonomics.com/norway-toxic-trickle-down-david-sloan-wilson/">Wlison and Hessen (2015)</a>.
(My emphasis)</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The success of the so-called “Nordic Model” is commonly attributed to factors such as income equality, a high level of trust, high willingness to pay tax, which is tightly coupled to strong social security (health, education), a blend of governmental regulations and capitalism, and cultural homogeneity. These and other factors are important, but we think that viewing them through an evolutionary lens is likely to shed light on why they are important. Our hypothesis is that <strong>Norway functions well as a nation because it has successfully managed to scale up the social control mechanisms that operate spontaneously in village-sized groups</strong>. Income equality, trust, and the other factors attributed to Norway’s success emanate from the social control mechanisms.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hypergranular Macroeconomics</title>
      <link>http://localhost/pde/posts/2019-01-28-hypergranular-macroeconomics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost/pde/posts/2019-01-28-hypergranular-macroeconomics/</guid>
      <description>The Bruegel blog of September 4, 2018 reports from the annual Jackson Hole gathering of central bankers. This year the focus was on implications for central banks of the rise of superstar firms and changing market structure. Of particular interest I found the contribution of Antoinette Schoar (MIT Sloan) - as refered by Bruegel:
Antoinette Schoar looks at the financial market, argues that the rapid growth of new digital technologies has created a market dynamic, where many institutions outside the central bank system might soon have much more comprehensive, more accurate and also more timely information than the regulators.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Bruegel blog of September 4, 2018 reports from the annual Jackson Hole gathering of central
bankers.
This year the focus was on implications for central banks of the rise of superstar firms and
changing market structure.
Of particular interest I found the contribution of Antoinette Schoar (MIT Sloan) -
as refered by Bruegel:</p>
<p><em>Antoinette Schoar looks at the financial market, argues that the rapid growth of new digital technologies has created a market dynamic, where many institutions outside the central bank system might soon have much more comprehensive, more accurate and also more timely information than the regulators. Companies like Google or Amazon can use their data to predict regional sales growth or job losses. Google Trends is just one example of the power of aggregation from individual search information. This poses a challenge going forward that is structural and intellectual. On the one hand we need to think about how central banks can get visibility of the types of data that private-sector institutions are collecting as part of their core business. On the intellectual side the availability of this hyper-granular data asks for a new way of building economic models based on individual purchase or borrowing decisions. This is a challenge to the whole field of (macro)economics.</em></p>
<p><a href="http://bruegel.org/2018/09/monetary-policy-and-superstar-firms/">Bruegel on monetary policy and superstar firms</a></p>
<p><a href="https://bruegel.us1.list-manage.com/track/click?u=b654eefc55844506fec2d988b&amp;id=56b3a386d7&amp;e=cc7b5caad3">Antoinette Schoar (pdf)</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Krugmans Explanations</title>
      <link>http://localhost/pde/posts/2018-01-25-krugmans-explanations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost/pde/posts/2018-01-25-krugmans-explanations/</guid>
      <description>Mainstream economics failure to &amp;lsquo;see the crisis coming&amp;rsquo; in 2008 is broadly regarded as a deficiency of the theory. However, Paul Krugman now argues that the theory was - and is - &amp;lsquo;good enough for government&amp;rsquo;. The failure of 2008 was not in the theory, but rather in deficient data collection. Macroeconomists &amp;ldquo;overlooked&amp;rdquo; the institutional changes in the financial sector and did not record appropriate data.
The &amp;ldquo;New Keynesians&amp;rdquo; - i.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Mainstream economics failure to &lsquo;see the crisis coming&rsquo; in 2008
is broadly regarded as a deficiency of the theory.
However, Paul Krugman now argues that the theory was - and is - &lsquo;good
enough for government&rsquo;. The failure of 2008 was not in the theory,
but rather in deficient <em>data collection</em>. Macroeconomists &ldquo;overlooked&rdquo;
the institutional changes in the financial sector
and did not record appropriate data.</p>
<p>The &ldquo;New Keynesians&rdquo; - i.e. Krugman&rsquo;s &lsquo;Saltwater School&rsquo; based at
MIT and Harvard - took up the challenge by <em>dust[ing] off their old sticky-price models from the 1950s and 1960s, which told them three things:</em></p>
<ol>
<li>Very large budget deficits would not drive up near-zero interest rates.</li>
<li>Even large increases in the monetary base would not lead to high inflation, or even to corresponding increases in broader monetary aggregates.</li>
<li>There would be a positive national income multiplier, almost surely greater than one, from changes in government spending and taxation.</li>
</ol>
<p>Krugman argues that these propositions made the case for budget deficits in the aftermath of the collapse of 2008 which worked “remarkably well.”
This New Keynesian policy was a succes - in contrast to the more inflexible
responses promoted by the &lsquo;Freshwater - Chicago School&rsquo;.</p>
<p>However, fiscal expansion was soon replaced by austerity.</p>
<p>Krugman&rsquo;s version is not taken at face value by Robert Skidelsky who
argues that <em>when Keynes was briefly exhumed for six months in 2008-2009, it was for political, not intellectual, reasons. Because the New Keynesian models did not offer a sufficient basis for maintaining Keynesian policies once the economic emergency had been overcome, they were quickly abandoned.</em></p>
<p><em>The problem for New Keynesian macroeconomists is that they fail to acknowledge radical uncertainty in their models, leaving them without any theory of what to do in good times in order to avoid the bad times. Their focus on nominal wage and price rigidities implies that if these factors were absent, equilibrium would readily be achieved. They regard the financial sector as neutral, not as fundamental.</em></p>
<p><em>Without acknowledgement of uncertainty, saltwater economics is bound to collapse into its freshwater counterpart. New Keynesian “tweaking” will create limited political space for intervention, but not nearly enough to do a proper job. So Krugman’s argument, while provocative, is certainly not conclusive. Macroeconomics still needs to come up with a big new idea.</em></p>
<p><a href="https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/why-no-intellectual-shift-in-economics-by-robert-skidelsky-2018-01">Skidelsky</a></p>
<p><a href="https://academic.oup.com/oxrep/article/34/1-2/156/4781811">Krugman</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
