<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Capabilities on Dyrehaugen</title>
    <link>http://localhost/pde/tags/capabilities/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Capabilities on Dyrehaugen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost/pde/tags/capabilities/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Use it or loose it</title>
      <link>http://localhost/pde/posts/2017-06-20-use-it-or-loose-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost/pde/posts/2017-06-20-use-it-or-loose-it/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I got a reminder from Mars! There is a &amp;lsquo;Starmus&amp;rsquo; conference going on these days, in Trondheim, Norway. One astronaut told about returning to Earth after 43 days in Space - the message being that what you don&amp;rsquo;t use (in Space) you have lost when back (on Earth) - i.e. without gravity your sense of balance get lost - you have to retrain basic mobility capabilities upon return.
So also for elderly people - without exercising mind and body capabilities get lost.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I got a reminder from Mars!
There is a &lsquo;Starmus&rsquo; conference going on these days, in Trondheim, Norway.
One astronaut told about returning to Earth after 43 days in Space - the
message being that what you don&rsquo;t use (in Space) you have lost when back
(on Earth) - i.e. without gravity your sense of balance get lost - you
have to retrain basic mobility capabilities upon return.</p>
<p>So also for elderly people - without exercising mind and body capabilities
get lost. Thats why daily dogwalking keeps me (and the dogs) going.</p>
<p>Beware also the mental vulnurality. Who recalls phone numbers these days?
Say your phone got missed and you need to ask someone else to make a call
for you - would you be able to tell the number to dial?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
