<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Aristocracy on Dyrehaugen</title>
    <link>http://localhost/pde/tags/aristocracy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Aristocracy on Dyrehaugen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost/pde/tags/aristocracy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Some Time Soon</title>
      <link>http://localhost/pde/posts/2021-01-12-some-time-soon/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost/pde/posts/2021-01-12-some-time-soon/</guid>
      <description>Some Time Soon - things will be the same, but different.
However, we did not notice the emerging change? - or did we?
 David Roberts tweet the day after the Trump-mob storm on Capitol: Feels like we&amp;rsquo;re trapped in a script, a play, that has been performed several times around the world recently. And even though we know exactly how the fall-of-democracy script plays out &amp;ndash; every beat, every chapter &amp;ndash; we&amp;rsquo;re just trapped, helpless, watching it play out</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Some Time Soon - things will be the same, but different.</p>
<p>However, we did not notice the emerging change? - or did we?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>David Roberts tweet the day after the Trump-mob storm on Capitol:
Feels like we&rsquo;re trapped in a script, a play,
that has been performed several times around the world recently.
And even though we know exactly how the fall-of-democracy script plays
out &ndash; every beat, every chapter &ndash; we&rsquo;re just trapped, helpless,
watching it play out</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In 2018 Matthew Stewart had an excellent
<a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2018/06/the-birth-of-a-new-american-aristocracy/559130/">piece</a>
in the Atlantic on the morphing of the upper 9.9 percent of American wealth-distribution
into a new <em>Aristocracy</em>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Perhaps the best evidence for the power of an aristocracy is
the degree of resentment it provokes (Matthew Stewart)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Trump is a smart entrepreneur - first in business, then in politics.
Before other he saw the vote potential in the resentment against this new aristocracy -
The Washington Swamp.</p>
<p>Trump succeeded in creating a bizarre aliance between ultra-rich
and the left-behinds of the neoliberal era -
picking up enough votes to start an attack on the ruling aristocracy.</p>
<p>230 years have gone since the French Revolution -
and we still have not seen the return of the pitchforks.</p>
<p>Obama sold &lsquo;change&rsquo; without delivering.
Trump makes &lsquo;change&rsquo;, but only for the benefit of the ultra-rich.
His attacks on the aristocracy in Washington is enough to get him going
with the resentfull.</p>
<p>The aristocracy managed to overturn their 2016-loss with at call
for &lsquo;healing of the nation&rsquo;.
But how should this healing occur?
Only removal of the aristocracy will satisfy the resentfull.
That will not happen witouth the pitchforks.
Some time soon  there is worse to come.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
